Fred Stark Pearson Papers MS141
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Fred Stark Pearson Papers
1885 -- 1928, 2019
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Pearson, Fred Stark
MS141
0.25 Linear Feet 1 box
4 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series.
Custodial History
This collection incorporates previously un-cataloged items and material from the dismantled vertical file on Fred Stark Pearson, as well as a later donation of a published volume on Pearson.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes posthumous correspondence, newspaper clippings, journal articles, biographical essays, obituaries, a photograph, an unpublished manuscript, and a published volume on Pearson.
Biographical / Historical
Fred Stark Pearson (FSP) was born on July 3, 1861. After his father, an engineer on the Boston and Lowell Railroad, died in 1876, the family moved to Medford where FSP began work as a railroad station agent. His skill and intelligence drew the attention of members of the Tufts faculty, and Amos Dolbear convinced him to enroll at Tufts. FSP graduated from Tufts with a Bachelor of Civil Engineering in 1883 and a Master of Mechanic Arts in 1884.
After graduating, FSP served for three years as an instructor in mathematics at Tufts. He then went on to a brilliant engineering career. For his first job for the West End Street Railway of Boston he helped develop steam-generated electricity to run trolleys. Based on this success, he became a consulting engineer to many railways in the U.S. and Canada. He also consulted for civil engineering projects, including the reconstruction of shipping piers and the improvement of coal handling and mining equipment. FSP was greatly interested in long-distance power transmission and water power.
In 1899, he got involved in a project that led to the development of hydro-electric power for São Paulo; he was subsequently involved in similar projects elsewhere in Brazil, Mexico, and Canada. His final major project was to harness the Ebro River to bring power to Barcelona, Spain. Needing to attend a crucial business meeting related to this project, FSP set sail on the ill-fated Lusitania. FSP and his wife Mabel Ward Pearson died on May 7, 1915 when the Lusitania sank, damaged by a German torpedo.
Through his engineering ventures and business investments, FSP became very wealthy. He donated frequently and generously to Tufts. FSP became a Trustee of Tufts in 1900, received an honorary Doctor of Science in 1900, and an honorary Doctor of Laws in 1905.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
"The Existential Joys of Fred Stark Pearson," by Gilmore G. Cooke, was a gift of Gilmore G. Cooke, MS-2020-017.
Pearson, Frederick Stark; Alumni collections
- Fred Stark Pearson papers, 1885 -- 1928, 2019; MS141.001; 0.25 Linear Feet; 4 Digital Object(s); 1 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains posthumous correspondence, newspaper clippings, journal articles, biographical essays, obituaries, a photograph, and an unpublished manuscript, all of which are about FSP.
  Arrangement
  This series is not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Fred Stark Pearson papers, 1 of 2, MS141.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Fred Stark Pearson papers, 2 of 2, MS141.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript on Fred Stark Pearson by Stearns Morse, MS141.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    This may be a chapter from Stearns Morse's unpublished book "The Yankee Spirit", considered the best source of biographical information on FSP and held in the Brascan Archives, Toronto. (Armstrong, C. and H.V. Nelles, "A Curious Capital Flow: Canadian Investment in Mexico, 1902-1910," Business History Review, 58.2, 1984.)
  - Fred Stark Pearson memorial album, 1928; MS141.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Dedication of memorial to Fred Stark Pearson in Barcelona, Spain (front view), 1928-05-19; MS141.001.DO.00011; Unknown (Box Shared 83)
    Events; Memorials; People; photographic print; Pearson, Fred Stark
  - Dedication of memorial to Fred Stark Pearson in Barcelona, Spain (side view), 1928-05-19; MS141.001.DO.00012; Unknown (Box Shared 83)
  - Fred Stark Pearson, 1905; MS141.001.DO.00013; Unknown (Box Shared 143)
    People; Portraits; Alumni and alumnae; photographic print; Pearson, Fred Stark
  - Fred Stark Pearson, 1885; MS141.001.DO.00014; Hardy (Box Shared 143)
  - "The Existential Joys of Fred Stark Pearson (1861-1915): Engineer, Entrepreneur, Envisioner," by Gilmore G. Cooke, 2019; MS141.001.00015; 1 Volumes (Volume 1)
    Pearson, Fred Stark